Douglas rushkoff has been described as
one of the world's 10 most influential
thinkers he began his career documenting
the psychedelic culture that created the
early internet then with books like
throwing rocks at the Google bus he
started sounding the alarm about what
technology was doing to society he
subscribed his most recent book team
human as a mic drop moment and a
manifesto to recover human values in a
digital age
Douglas thank you for making the time to
do this this is actually the second time
we've done an interview and the first
time was one of the very few occasions
that we had technical problems and it
ended up being unusable so thank you for
making time the second time and I guess
the good thing is that I can remember
some of the good answers that you gave
last time so we can kind of dive into
that I hope and I'm really looking
forward to this because your your recent
book team human and the trajectory that
you've been on seems very similar to the
trajectory that we've been on since the
beginning of the channel kind of really
coming home to real conversations human
contact and how that's really important
for getting out of some of the cultural
kind of messes that we seem to have got
ourselves into
so I I'd love to hear what what has your
kind of journey with this being like
well my journeys been a long one you
know I mean for me it started with with
theater really and I was I was
interested in in well I was interested
in theater and medicine at the same time
because I wanted to know what what
animated human beings you know what's
the difference between the living one
and a dead one and you know the medicine
and biology are really interested in
that you know what what constitutes life
when does when does physics or chemistry
become biology and theater is interested
in that because what we're trying to do
is to figure out what is a human being
in action what is this what is a person
what is intention what is their will you
know
and I played with both and got
disillusioned with both I got
disillusioned with medicine because it
was way too empirical you know there
wasn't any vitalism in it there was
nothing it didn't acknowledge the
weirdness that actually keeps us going
and theater I got sick of because it was
so expensive for people to go to and
elitist and closed-ended every play kind
of ended the same way you know and in
some tragedy or marriage you know big
crisis climax completion and right
around then the internet came around and
it seemed to answer all of my needs for
an egalitarian people's participatory
medium where instead of watching some
hero do stuff you are the hero you're
engaging and then you're not just
engaging in fiction you're engaging for
real in this kind of fact-based world
and now we can start solving solutions
together and bottom-up ways and remake
the economy to be circular instead of
extractive and change institutions and
relationships and I got excited but then
by the mid to late 90s once the internet
also became the poster child for the
Nasdaq Stock Exchange and big business
they pivoted the net from a people's
medium a connecting people's medium to a
data extraction platform and all of
these tools all of the software all
these devices were really programmed to
keep us apart from one another and turn
us back into isolated individual
manipulable customers and voters and
machines really so I guess what that
what I came all the way back around to
was that you know people actually have
the ability to connect you know without
anything without even without theater
for bid or without without a machine
without a device without a game that
people can can recalibrate themselves
really simply and easily just by making
eye contact for five seconds you undo
you know 10 hours of computer addiction
and and alienation and atomization so
now I'm really kind of all about helping
people find the opportunities and the
courage to engage with one another in
the flesh in real ways you know in in
real spaces and that that's the great
conspiracy that's literally what the
word conspiracy means - conspires to
breathe together you know so people
breathing together constitutes a
conspiracy against the dehumanizing
forces of of digital capitalism and how
would you summarize team human as your
contribution to that
well team human really started as a way
originally for me to have an excuse to
engage with other people and it's it's
turned into a way for me to kind of
amplify and spread the messages of
others rather than myself and I've
written 20 books and made all these
documentaries and done all this it's
like I feel like I've made my
contribution or gotten as much attention
as any person deserves and the best
thing I can do with that attention is
highlight you know people who are
helping us restore those the those human
connections and really the value of
being human you know human beings are
our at least in in Silicon Valley terms
human beings aren't understood as the
problem and technology is the solution
you know when you look at any human
problem from climate change to racism to
everything and we'll say oh that's
because of those humans and we've got to
develop better platforms and better
systems and so you know you know this
the systems and the platforms that are
corrupting the humans I think and I'm
sort of dedicating you know team human
to the the celebration of the weirdness
of the this
between the lines the things about us
that can't be quantized by digital
technology know nothing against digital
and and we are for sure we're migrating
into a digital media environment but if
we're gonna do that we better start
compensating now for what digital
doesn't recognize what aspects of
humanity does digital not see you know
just as we understand you know Marx
showed us how industrialism doesn't
respect the human worker
Digital doesn't respect the human
weirdness it doesn't respect the stuff
that can't be quantized the liminal
things between the lines you know the
the strangeness of human experience you
know in our in our you know and i
understand i are understandable quest to
you know upload consciousness to a
machine or to augment ourselves with
some kind of digital robotic sensor
matrix thing where we're too ready to
dismiss the stuff that can't get
uploaded as noise as meaningless and
it's not noise that's if anything that's
the signal you know whatever it is that
can't be repeated digitally that can't
be copied that's the stuff that's most
valuable but it's the stuff we have to
save there's a there's a concept called
spiritual bypass that i'm not sure if
whether you're familiar with that
there's something about that in this
kind of the big tech view of human
nature it's kind of almost like a human
bypass I mean I don't know about
spiritual bypass but you mean the the I
mean I do think that there's a a anti
spiritual premise and in Silicon Valley
it doesn't mean they don't have their
own religion but they think of
themselves as anti spiritual
materialists who are simply observing
information
evolving through increasingly complex
states and that as long as information
is is here it's going to look for more
complex kind of hosts so it moves from
you know atoms to molecules to
organelles to organisms to culture and
eventually to computers and at that
point when computers and quantum
computing or whatever it is an AI are
more complex than we are then
information continues its journey
without us and we can just you know fall
by the wayside and I would argue that's
anti spiritual I think they would say it
is spiritual Kurzweil would say well
that's more spiritual than anything and
that I'm being an egocentric
human you know and and and that I'm that
I'm I'm a shill for team human I mean
but that's that's what I am I'm a shill
for team human I'm I'm asking the
question about would it be so terrible
to keep us around
you know maybe do we have a role is
there something that we do that our
computers don't and can't and I think
there is I think that we're I think
we're special I think we have soul I
think there's a a a formal cause to
humanity you know and that's really what
what Aristotle would have called psyche
and we would call soul and it's it's
difficult to to describe and like you
know Francis Bacon empirical scientific
terms but it doesn't mean it's not it's
not real
you know it's what's holding you
together what's what's organizing you
what's the impetus for all this and
until we know that I'm not comfortable
cutting ties with with it with with the
the sort of the formal causes of of us
that's a really interesting frame I
guess of the the kind of implicit
cosmology structure of kind of Silicon
Valley which I'm slightly surprised
about given the influence of something
like Burning Man and the influence of
psychedelics on the big
of that was it ever was ever different
yeah I do get I mean it was different
right it was different when it was the
Grateful Dead heads running Silicon
Valley when it was the really sort of
early even pre Steve Jobs you know
computer clubs and homebrew stuff and
the well and the Merry Pranksters and
all there was a much crunchy er San
Francisco vibe to all of this I mean
when money came in and the Libertarians
came in it it became something else you
know then then the California ideology
was born and they would argue it's much
more rational you know but it's it's
actually kind of insane it's what leads
to the the the ego mania and and
acceleration ISM and and sort of
exponential mindset you know the only
thing that grows exponentially in nature
is cancer and it kills the host you know
you can't you can't use an exponential
model for human society or for human
marketplaces or anything that's just
it's just then it's people serving
balance sheets it's people serving
numbers even the billionaires don't need
that accumulation you don't need a
trillion dollars you don't need multiple
billions you really be okay with even
just tens of millions you'll somehow
survive it pretty much the same level I
think you know so so how does that
excess happen that just happens because
the the the program is bad you know and
they think it's they think they're
optimizing the program by leading to
creating all this extraction but it's
not it's not it's it's it's out of its
out of sync with anything that matters
or so it's a I don't know if that
answers your question well if it doesn't
it was a really nice digression so it
was probably better than you answering
the question are you familiar with the
concept of the the paperclip maximized
which I don't think it originated with
Daniel SHM actin burger but he did a
good podcast with Charles Eisenstein
about it no tell me so it's kind of
implicit in what you were just I do get
concerned it's funny the way we're
talking it's again it's it's there's a
lot of white guys in their 30s and 40s
you know it's like you and me and
Charles on this guy and say we're just
talking about all these dudes you know
and it's it's interesting so it there's
there's something about even this great
conversation that still ends up feeling
like you know stone guys in a good Ivy
League dorm room you know talking about
the future of our species it's part of
the problem is that we end up with
there's a particular kind of thinking
that that we all do as kind of
college-educated nerdy white men that's
just it feels a little digital to me it
feels a little bit like we know how to
make these points but we're missing all
that space between the points you know
and that's I mean that's the problem
with any intellectual heady
philosophical discussion about about the
world and it's kind of why I and you
here even when I talk about it now I
talk so little about to my ideas and so
much more about kind of history like
this telling the story this is what
happened and here's who took over and
here's why these kids felt this way
and it is I mean the the question you
were asking before is basically how can
these people go to places like Burning
Man or go down to South America and do
ayahuasca and trip their brains out and
still be assholes you know
that's sort of that was the question
that was bothering me for the last 10
years or so and I remember it was it was
actually longer was when I was in
college and I tripped and said oh my god
now I see how everything's connected and
then I saw there's people tripping in
the parking lot of the ac/dc concert
who's still just like they
trip and they break glass and stuff and
smash beer bottles and it's like wait a
minute you're trippin shouldn't you be
seeing the clear light of the essential
human experience and now you're just
being assholes and that's why
you can have the chairman of Google and
Apple and everything they can go and
they can have these experiences and they
can hear the earth you know cry to them
but then they're going to conclude that
oh and the way I'm gonna fix all this is
by you know bringing the world's
information to them through a good
search engine or you know creating
electric cars and spaceships and get us
off the planet knob so you know just
because you've gone to Burning Man or
had one of these experiences doesn't
mean that you are ready to embrace the
full spectrum of humanity it's for a lot
of people it doesn't really crash the
walls of ego at all but in some ways and
some in some cases makes them more rigid
you know which is it's it's surprising
but again it's what Timothy Leary used
to talk about way back when it's you're
set in your setting what set and setting
are you doing this are you doing it in a
way are you really willing to to rip
open the fabric of reality and challenge
who wouldn't who you are and what you've
lived for or you just want to have a
good pyrotechnic kind of Disney
experience or also the idea that
psychedelics are just a nuns or are a
nonspecific amplifier you're not
necessarily for you or for me it might
be amplifying that sort of more
spiritual dimension but then it can
amplify any any dimension there's no
kind of necessarily it's kind of an
amoral thing and I was hoping it wasn't
you know I didn't think it was you know
I originally thought well maybe LSD and
some of the chemical synthetic chemical
psychedelics are amoral but you know the
vision vine from the forest peoples
would somehow let the
spirit of the earth speak to speak to a
person you know that those have sort of
more personality or voices in them and
again I guess they have voices in them
for certain people and different voices
for others
I first became aware of your work
through the throwing rocks at the Google
bus book and it was actually only sort
of in the in the run-up to the last
interview that I was aware of sort of
your your interest in the psychedelic
world and your long kind of history with
with this conversation could you could
you describe a little bit of that what
what what was your background in that I
know that you were you were friends with
Timothy Leary is that is that right and
you were also connected to Robert Anton
Wilson could you could you describe a
little bit or explain some of that
history it's a different era you know
the late 80s and early 90s and it was in
some ways easier to find people and
connect with them and if you were
willing you know it was theirs people
were more naive to about things you
could go somewhere and say you're gonna
write an article or do a book on
something people just spoke with you
everybody was candid now you know people
are different about news everybody's
kind of media savvy and they want a
piece of it oh you're writing a book
well what am I gonna get you know and
it's publicity you know they don't just
let you walk around with them and and
and chill so you know I was living in
Los Angeles and interested in a lot of
these sort of early crazy cyber stories
I was interested in why were my most
psychedelic friends from college moving
out to Silicon Valley and becoming
computer people because these were not
computer types these were Grateful Dead
heads these were you know a creative
theater artsy people doing computer so I
started following that and seeing that
oh I get it it's because these
technologies are so hallucinatory that
you need people well-versed and
hallucinations to play with them to feel
confident enough to render these worlds
that the rest of humanity was going to
be living in I was just kind of welcomed
in as a you know young member of this
community that that realized that you
know digital was the next landscape for
human consciousness and that was this
something big was happening you know the
counterculture saw digital first we
couldn't hold on to it but but we saw it
first so they just became you know
friends and mentors and you know I
mentioned Robert Anton Wilson
specifically because that names come up
quite a few times recently we did an
interview with Eric Davis about he's
just done a book called high weirdness
that is partly about Robert Anton Wilson
and then Jamie will mentioned him as
well as as realizing how much of an
impact reading him as a as a young man
has had on him since the concepts of
reality tunnels and the kind of the idea
of sort of fake news or conspiracy
theory it's sort of going deeply into
conspiracy theory in reality tunnels in
particular seems to kind of define the
modern world probably as well as
anything would you agree yeah I mean his
idea of reality tunnels is what now in a
digital age we're calling filter bubbles
you know except you know reality tunnels
were kind of more self-composed where
filter bubbles are composed by
algorithms on our behalf you know and
that's that's a little different you
know so so we're not totally in control
of it you know it's it's one thing when
we're all looking at the same reality
and then devising our own
interpretations or tunnels from it it's
different when we're all being shown
different realities and coming up with
our own tunnels so it's really hard to
find to find common ground but the other
thing that he was part of was you know
operation mindfuck operation mindfuck
was like the the it's what's today's
become fake news operation mindfuck was
a counterculture technique to
really toy with people's reality you
know even though we're gonna levitate
the Pentagon and we did it you know and
then it you create such cognitive
dissonance that people don't know what
to trust anymore and the idea was it
would break open mainstream culture it
would help break people of the kind of
consumerist illusion of mainstream
culture challenge their reality going to
social ana.k almost yeah but I mean
we're real a genuine social anarchy
it requires human beings who are at
least you know functioning with some
pretense of compassion it's funny I
wrote a book on on Judaism way back when
and I was arguing that Judaism is sort
of it's all it's all captured by Joan
Rivers when she used to say can we talk
can we talk she'd always say can we talk
and can we talk means can we talk can we
be frank here can we actually say this
is right this is not real this
is it's just you and me right and all
this social constructionism can we talk
but in order to talk she had she had
this other line she is to say when she
would say a joke and the audience would
would freak out she would say Oh grow up
grow up and that's the thing you've got
to be an adult to just have that
conversation you've got to grow up and
right now it's like children it's little
kids you know when I look at Trump the
the main vibe I get it's like ass of a 5
year old or a 6 year old who's like kind
of been naughty and is trying to make
excuse it he's he's immature
is the problem if you don't go through
adolescence
you can't engage in this reality hacking
there's this sort of sense of the
psychedelic revolution merging with the
the kind of the tech world and I think
you said in our first interview
something like what was it Silicon
Valley dropped acid and now everyone's
having a bad trip
I wouldn't say it has to do with
psychedelics in particular I mean when
when I was with Timothy when he
went on the web for the first time and
he said this is acid that this is as
powerful as acid and it's going to be
more powerful because people don't need
to ingest it in order to trip in order
to have this internet experience and the
thing leer it used to say about acid
before you take acid is that you've got
to be aware of your set and your setting
in other words what's the mindset that
you're bringing to it and what's the
physical setting where you're gonna do
it you know so if you're you know you
know doing it in a war zone that might
not be the best way to trip or if you're
starting a trip where you're thinking
how am I going to make the most money by
exploiting people and then you're
dropping acid with that mindset that's
not going to lead you to a happy
tripping place and I was thinking about
you know if the if the digital realm is
as powerful as acid you know what set
and setting are we bringing to it you
know we originally brought the set of
you know human potential and infinite
connection between others and now the
set and setting of the Internet is
extractive surveillance capitalism so if
the world is now living in a psychedelic
substrate for the last 20 years with a
set and setting of extraction abuse
manipulation and and surveillance
capitalism you know no wonder we're
having a bad trip you know this this
this is where we're at and I understand
people are having this they're waking up
into a nightmarish bad trip and that's
why their behaviors like this that's why
their voting is like this that's why
their their various forms of denial and
hate and and isolation and despair I
can't imagine what it would be to have
those sensibilities amplified you know
by this kind of maelstrom of digital
tech is that I mean how would you
summarize that is that because basically
our connections between each other and
our
as social space has been exploited and
weaponized to the point where even even
sort of genuine interactions are being
monetized and being extracted by this
model is that a summer sort of similar
summary yeah we are living with
technologies that are intentionally
designed to make us fearful to make us
panic to put us back into our brainstem
to avoid our higher human thinking and
our even our mammalian thinking and then
sometimes we're trying to connect with
other people over devices that are
designed to make us hate and fear the
other person designed to a dict us to
the tech designed to get us to interact
with non-player characters algorithms
rather than other people and then we
wonder why we feel bad you know if you
live in a in a digital haunted house
that's designed by Stanford behavioral
engineers to make you hate to make you
fear what do you think's gonna happen
you know it's just aspect and then you
grow up in it as a child I mean what do
you think's gonna happen to those brains
what do you think is gonna happen to
those to those hearts what do we do
about it well the easiest thing to do is
to connect with other people in real
life meet people kiss them hug them sit
with them you know it's the easiest way
I mean these are technologies that are
designed to de calibrate you to make you
uneasy to disconnect you from any kind
of natural circadian or other rhythm so
the way to to restore that rhythm is you
look in somebody else's eyes for five
seconds breathe together you know the
congrates conspiracy just breathe
together with someone else and all of
these painstakingly evolved mechanisms
for social coherence get reactivated you
know we evolved to make eye contact
that's why human beings have the most
white in their eyes it's so that babies
can can really target and see
what where's the mother looking where's
the mother's gaze that this is part of
it and when you make that connection
that eye connection not over Skype but
in real life um your mirror neurons fire
the oxytocin goes through your
bloodstream you begin to establish
rapport and you start to move into sync
with the other person that's and I hate
to use a word like this but that's the
natural human condition that's the way
we make sense that's the way we
stabilize and normalize our our
constitutions that's the way we build
the frameworks that establish a society
you can't do that however much we like
to think we can we can't do that through
spreadsheets and it's a sort of
utilitarian things so the blockchain
will not unite humanity it could
organize our numbers but that's not
where that's not where the show is
that's not where where this is actually
happening I know I think you're also
familiar with polyvagal theory we did a
whole series around the the psychology
the science and psychology of
polarization and the science and
psychology of difficult conversation and
found that frame polyvagal theory
understanding exactly that how we're
intrinsically social we're constantly
looking for connections with others and
with and it's generally moderated by the
the vagus nerve and I think you
mentioned it a little bit in your in
your book for me that feels like a
really important thing for us to realize
and when we interviewed Steven Porges he
called it the neurobiology of
spirituality and religion as much as it
was the neurobiology of kind of
difficult conversations it's funny we
call it spiritual you know when we talk
about human beings being connected
subtly is one great organism we call it
spiritual but when we look at the fact
that all the cells in your body are
joined together to create this one thing
we call that science you know it's
interesting it's interesting what we
still don't know why all the cells work
together and why we don't just follow up
I mean I know why we stick together but
we don't know what they know and why
they all do their job
and coordinate this being I mean my my
god you know that's just as as weird
just as strange it's just we're more
used to it but yeah polyvagal theory as
the the aspect of it that's most useful
to me is the idea that our nervous
systems are not our own you are not a
distinct nervous system you are part of
a much bigger nervous system and when
stuff happens to your nervous system
that changes mine and mine changes yours
and everybody around that the reason why
you need to get your act together is
because the rest of us are living with
you the rest of us are impacted by your
nervous system and it's fucked-up-ness
you know so it's hard enough you know on
our families and our loved ones and the
people who are right with us dealing
with our the actual behaviors but
everybody is dealing with the
incoherence you know so we kind of owe
it to our collective organism to be as
coherent as possible and if we can't be
coherent then we should at least be
quiet yeah I think this is a point
that's been made before that in a world
of ever-expanding exponential tech no
one gets to be completely up
right well if you're completely
up and you're at the dashboard of you
know the of the net or even if you've
got a powerful twitter account you cause
a whole lot more damage than you did it
used to be just some guy would you know
stand on an Apple crate in the park and
say weird stuff I mean and now the
weirdest people and not weird in the fun
way but weird in the destructive way
have tremendous mouthpieces
you know they'd get tremendous
amplification and then when you combine
that with the fact that they're being
amplified on a platform that's been
designed to put people into a state of
terror
they're going to get more amplification
than
those of us who are arguing for
rapprochement or moderation or even
tolerance yeah and you'd be a good
person to ask about this we had a had a
dialogue with Josh fields the CEO of
consciousness hacking so their idea is
that it's possible it's it's not
implicit in tech it's just the first
generation of tools that we have and the
potentially tech could also be the
solution as well as the as well as the
problem do you have time for that
argument or do you think there are
incentives or characteristics built into
the world of tech that will will kind of
act against that kind of slightly more
optimistic vision I mean I have time for
the argument but I think it's wrong you
know I mean it's like okay now because
my smartphone is making me crazy
I can now install a wellness app to try
to counteract the crazy that the rest of
the cell phone has put on me I mean as a
baby step maybe you know if people are
so addicted to the thing that the only
place to get them less addicted is
through the thing itself you know it's
like Jesus going into the you know
temple with the money changers or
something but it's so much so much
easier than that so no I don't I don't
believe at this stage of civilization
that we should be turning to digital
devices for correctives to the problem
of digital technology I I don't I don't
see it I think it's it's a desperate
attempt mostly of mostly of digital
business and people who have such a
stake in it to think that there's a way
out that's that's through and and I
don't I don't think there is it's the
same question as weird
the topsoil we've got you know 30
harvests left before it's all gone do we
retrieve the aboriginal permaculture
methods and crop rotation and treating
the soil like a living matrix and do we
do we do we retrieve those sort of more
ancient approaches to life and
circularity or do we pedal-to-the-metal
investin Monsanto and figure out how to
use chemicals to grow more crops on
rocks or on the ocean or figure out how
to eat salt and and and I think there's
still enough I think we're still early
enough in our descent to retrieve you
know III still think we are we are close
enough to the shore of a natural human
existence to rely on terra firma for our
wellness but it's possible there'll be
some day when we are so when we're so
far from what we think of human you know
when maybe the human body is itself
dispersed on two chips on two quantum
machines where we don't really have
faces anymore whatever and at that point
yeah some sense of wellness and those
cells and those last remaining
biological elements of the computers
yeah that they're gonna need to be
massaged by apps in order to you know
resonate on some biological level I just
I just don't think we're there well you
don't think it's possible that for
example we have social media apps at the
moment that are kind of hijacking our
limbic system going for outrage going
for kind of the the quick dopamine hit
and response and you don't think it's
possible for that to shift so we have
maybe algorithms that were designed
towards growth and towards kind of a
more kind of the higher angels of our
nature or the better angels of our
nature if you put a whole culture on
dexedrine because you want them to be
faster oh they're do oh it look how fast
they're going this is great
but they're having trouble falling
asleep now and they're not dreaming and
they're getting upset okay what do we do
well could we invent a drug that will
help them sleep while they're on
dexedrine sure let's do it let's do into
valium and domain and and dilaudid and
things to help them sleep oh sure
you can create compensatory tech for the
tech that we're using but the best way
to compensate for it is to embed oneself
in nature in connection with others in
in humans you calibrate better looking
face-to-face at another human you could
create a calibration routine that put
two eyes and a and and irises and a
vibration on a screen so you stare at
those eyes and slowly recalibrate your
system not as well as with a person
because we don't know all the mechanisms
that we've evolved for establishing
connection with others but you could
create an ultra simplified hack of your
brain to fool it into thinking it's
getting calibrated the same way you can
listen to an mp3 file of a song and fool
your brain into thinking it's listening
to music when it's not it's listening to
an algorithmic recreation of certain
aspects of music in order to convince
your brain that you're hearing based but
there's no bass going in your body
there's nothing there so yes we can do
artificial things to create compensatory
compromised experiences but there's
still food you could eat you know so you
don't have to just have protein powders
there's still people you can have sex
with so you don't have to use porn and
there's still nature so you don't have
to use tech in order to calibrate your
organism to reality
you know what I mean we're not we're not
in space we're not in space if you're if
you're alone in space you're on the
space station what are you gonna do okay
let's give that guy some apps to
recreate you know what things are I give
them a sex doll I'll give them
everything that that you got right
because she's stuck there in that in a
and a Space Station you know and it but
I look at you know we send my daughter
off to school and make her lunch and
there's like these things wrapped in
plastics and in yogurt enough thing it's
like that's like spaceman food what are
we doing what are we doing right that's
we act as if we're living on a space
station
that's how hermetically sealed
everything we're using is and that's
crazy
and that's why we're all getting
allergies and autoimmune diseases and
stuff it's like everything's gotten too
packaged and sterile and plastic and and
nuts this is killing it and we have a
lot of people on our channel talking
about existential risk and you've
described how there was a story you told
about being kind of invited in by a load
of Silicon Valley guys who are basically
asking you what would happen when the
Cataclysm came I don't know if you feel
comfortable kind of repeating that story
I'd like to I got a couple of questions
I'd like to ask about that so yeah I I
was invited to do what I thought was a
talk to like bankers or something at a
resort and instead of me going out on
stage to do a talk they brought these
five guys into the greenroom who started
peppering me with all these questions
about the digital future you know like
you know Bitcoin or aetherium and
augmented reality or virtual reality I
figured it was one of these things where
it's just these five billionaire's
looking for you know investment
strategies from someone who's on the
ground in the cyber revolution and
eventually they got around to the
question of you know Alaska or New
Zealand right so they wanted to know
mainly how to prepare for the inevitable
collapse of society and the question we
spent most of the time on was how do I
maintain control of my security force
after the event because their money's
gonna be worthless and these guys will
turn on them and it just struck me that
here are the wealthiest and most
powerful men I've ever encountered yet
they feel utterly powerless to influence
the digital future that the best they
can do is prepare for the inevitable
collapse and you know insulate
themselves from the reality that they're
creating by earning money in the way
they're earning it and it was it was sad
but it was indicative of the way these
folks are thinking you know the the high
level billionaires like that Elon Musk's
and Jeff Bezos they want to get off the
planet altogether really just leave us
behind
but the mid-level billionaires who can't
afford rocket chips there want to build
you know bunkers and secret communities
and get robot guards and you know and to
protect themselves from the rest of us
you know they really think that this is
that this is where it's going or at
least they they're they're convinced
enough that they're putting in 20 30
percent of their wealth into these
survivalists and areas and it's just
it's a it's a it's a dark place for us
to have gotten you know particularly the
people who are building the
technological infrastructure yeah and I
think your conclusion to that was well
if you want to stop your your kind of
security force basically mutinying
you're gonna have to treat them well
basically what the only things that
actually going to be useful in those
environments are things like trust love
care and the soft skills because you
can't actually that the money isn't
gonna help right and our legacy of doing
that you can't just start when they
arrived I mean the joke was I said you
know if you really want you know you
want your head of security to protect
you you know pay for his daughter's Bat
Mitzvah today you know and they all
laugh because none of their heads of
security or Jewish guys with you know
daughters getting bat mitzvahs but they
understood what I meant you know if
you've paid for someone's daughter's Bat
Mitzvah then
when push comes to shove it's gonna be
hard for them to kill you you know 20
years later in the shelter because
they'll think this guy paid for my
daughter's Bat Mitzvah I can't just
can't just kill them and invite them
like the dudes but invite their families
too you know so that it's a community
but then you might as well invite
everybody so instead of figuring out how
to insulate yourself from the future
world what if you spent your effort
figuring out how to make the world a
place you don't need to insulate
yourself from you know which is the real
answer and they should be smart enough
for that and what was the impact of that
on you like that experience were you
shocked or surprised by it I was I guess
I was surprised by it because I figured
if I was ever in a place with really
rich people I be spending the time like
asking them for money to do a theater
project or something or you know and
instead I experienced them all as such
kind of low-level thinkers I mean
they're smart you know and they could
play out all of the walking-dead
scenarios with me which is where they're
at it's sort of they're all like SimCity
kind of people they all look at
everything from this no it's like a
programmers view a game developers view
so they're looking at the way the game
is being played and they've gotten to
the idea that there's going to be a Last
Man Standing that it's this weird poker
game and that one person's gonna end up
winning but being utterly alone I'm so I
guess that the thing that surprised me
was was there's sort of their inability
to think in certain ways kind of no
matter what books they read or they
can't think outside of this very
individualist understanding of things
I mean maybe it if partly it's what
happens when you get all this money that
people treat you differently so they are
really alone and they're in the worst
position possible but I don't see why it
necessarily has to happen that way but
yeah I was a little sad they just seemed
really young they seemed like they had
very childlike understandings of the
world but it's a lot of them you know
leave college they drop out of college
when they make their first million and
you know and keep going from there
because this is the kind of concern I
think that the I'm hearing from a lot of
people is this the potential for some
people in Silicon Valley to be kind of
thinking already thinking along those
lines and then why not just drive it off
the cliff we'll be okay
do you get that sense that that's
widespread or not
yeah it's either widespread that way or
they're cynically cynically thinking you
know none of us are gonna make it or you
know they remind me of I used to get
these dreams when I was a kid where I
like fall off a cliff or something but
then realize that I could kind of fly
and you don't just die and I think
they're thinking that that's gonna
something's going to happen that will
just prevent death and they're thinking
about death individually not even
civilizational II and that's uh it's
weird but yeah they're gonna upload
they're gonna something's gonna happen
before and that's you know they're so
disconnected from from others that I get
it death is really real to them and that
there's a question I wanted to ask that
we when we did our interview before just
before you got into the lift I don't
know if you remember this we touched on
a subject I said something like it seems
clear that the the only solution is
going to be somehow that we need to go
more into the liminal and you've sort of
looked at me and said yes definitely and
then then the lift doors closed and I
was like oh that should definitely have
been a big part of the interview so I
have a sense of what I meant by that but
I'd love to check with you what you
meant by that
well the liminal is a tricky concept for
a lot of people but I mean the easiest
way to describe it is you know we we
think about the tick
of the clock as the seconds but the
seconds are not the ticks the seconds
are the space between those ticks that's
where life happens that's where
everything happens
you know the digital realm understands
those ticks everything and it doesn't it
doesn't hear what's happening between
them and that's where love happens
that's where weirdness happens that's
where humanity lives is in the space
between the numbers and that's where
that's where we can play the place
between when you're awake and when
you're asleep the Eric Davis is wife
wrote that great book on you know that
kind of it's not lucid dreaming but it's
that that the in-between you know it's
it's as it's those transitions where
these these openings happen it's the
space between you and may it's not you
it's not me it's that ooh what is that
and those are the places that that
artists really toy with that's the
weirdness of a David Lynch movie it's
doesn't resolve it's not quite 1 or 0
it's just in that weird place and that's
I think that's our salvation you know
because that's where you can say to
people don't you see there's something
that's left behind and that that's
that's where we are that's our place is
that is that in between is that liminal
I'm not white I'm not black I'm not Jew
I'm not Christian I'm not alive I'm not
dead I'm not you know one I'm not many
what is you know what are all those
in-betweens you know that that the the
polarizing effective digital tech that
binary sequenced understanding of
reality doesn't acknowledge well done
for making it to the end I just wanted
to let you know a few things we've got
coming up including the biggest event
we've ever done the rebel wisdom
festival which will be a mix of ideas
and dialogues between people like
Douglas rushkoff Daniel SH maxim Berger
Bonita Roy Rupert Sheldrake John vivace
and many more and because wisdom isn't
just intellectual it's also
our practice will be offering
experiences like circling different
interpersonal dialogue mindfulness
breath work and many other with
world-class facilitators and if you're
enjoying the content you can help us
make more by joining the rebel wisdom
club which will give you discounts on
the courses and the events and also
access to a load more content on the
website including all of our live events
it'll also give you access to our
growing community which is something we
want to make a real focus for 2020
adding more meetups and other services
for members so I hope you enjoyed the
film and see you soon